Medieval and Renaissance Manuscripts Collection - Library Special Collections, ca. 1198-1616
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Charles E. Young Research Library: Department of Special Collections, Collection of Loose Leaves: ***170/403 (10 oversized ringed binders).
  - MISSAL. Germany, s. XII ¾., 2/XII/GER/1.; Fig. 10; Parchment, 1 leaf; 347 × 240 (243 × 170) mm. 24 long lines; ruling in lead; pricking in the inner, upper, and lower margins. Spiky, upright, rather compressed gothic bookhand in liturgical style (littera textualis format a), in two sizes. 2-line and 3/4-line initials in red capitals; initials in the text slashed with red; rubrics in red in the same script as the text; instructions to the rubricator in the inner margin. Almost contemporary marginalia by a German current gothic bookhand, on the recto “Thomae episcopi et martiris.. .”, on the verso “Genofeve virginis... Wilhelmi episcopi.. .”.
    r-v: // Secundum Matheum. In illo tempore. Angelus domini apparuit in somnis... supra serpentes et scorpiones et supra om// [sanctorale. from the Feast of the Innocents, 28 December, to the Feast of Felix, 14 January].
    Written in northern Germany, to judge from the parchment, script, and spelling. A fairly reliable terminus ante quern, 1170, is the added reference to St. Thomas of Canterbury. The conditions of preservation and “96” in pencil (s. XIX-XX) on the upper right-hand corner of the recto suggest that the leaf was part of a codex until the present century. Purchased from Dawson's Book Shop, Los Angeles; book-dealer's note in pencil: “1170. Spain. Missal. Revived Carolingian script.”
  - CANONICAL EPISTLES, with gloss. Switzerland or Germany, s. XII2., 2/XII/GER/2.; Parchment, 1 leaf; 220 × 145 (142 × 51, text; 155 × 140 with gloss) mm. Text on 1 column of 15 lines, gloss on 2 side columns; double bounding lines to the text, frame ruling to the gloss; drypoint ruling; slits in the outer margin and pricking at the top to guide the ruling. Spiky upright compressed twelfth-century ordinary minuscule script; dark brown ink for the text, brown for the gloss.
    r-v: //conspectu ecclesie quos benefaciens... scribere tibi spero autem protinus// [3 Ioh. 6-14, with marginal and interlinear gloss, apparently the standard glossatura parva].
    Written probably in Switzerland or southern Germany. The state of preservation, and “101” in ink (s. XIX) on the upper right-hand corner of the recto, suggest that the leaf was part of a codex until at least the nineteenth century. From the collection of Otto F. Ege; purchased by UCLA from Dawson's Book Shop, Los Angeles.
  - PSALTER. Germany, s. XII2., 1/XII/GER/3.; Parchment (coarse), 1 leaf; 210 × 153 (155 × 105) mm. 20 long lines; ruling not discernible. Spiky late Caroline minuscule script: shafts, both ascenders and minims, are wedge-shaped; brown ink. 4-line majuscule I in blue, surrounded by red, on the recto; initials of verses in red.
    r-v: //[salu]taris noster et averte iram... nomen tuum in eternum// [Ps. 84.5-85.12].
    Written in Germany. Parchment wrinkled and stained. Used for binding. Notes by a German cursive gothic hand on the verso, dated 1558. Notes in pencil in German (s. XX) on both recto and verso.
  - 1/XII/GER/4, Palimpsest.
    - Unidentified illegible text, primary script Germany (Uckerath?), s. XII., Parchment, 3 fragments that were formerly 2 leaves; 360 × 250 (ca. 310 × ca. 180) mm. 2 columns of ca. 36 lines. Late spiky ordinary minuscule verging to gothic; brown ink. Red initials and rubrics in red minuscule. Reduced to palimpsest in the late sixteenth century.
    - JOHANNES CRUPAEUS, REPORT ON THE TITHES OF UCKERATH, in German, secondary script. Germany (Uckerath), 1598., Parchment, 2 bifolia, the outer torn into 2 separate leaves; 250 × 180 mm. 27/29 long lines, perpendicular to the primary script, on ff. 2v-4; not ruled. Written in late German cursive gothic; grayish brown ink. Each folio is numbered in the lower right-hand recto, N. 1 to N. 4.
      ff. 1-4: f. 1 blank, except a note vertically written with the date 1565, corrected to 1665; f. 1v blank, remains of a seal. f. 2 [title, repeated below by a seventeenth-century hand] Nachricht über die Zehnden der pastoray Uckerath per Rev. dominum Johannem Crupaeum pastorem der selbs; ff. 2v-4 Des si auch wissen allen nimen nachkommen... daruff gedan [mentions the date 25 July 1598]; f. 4v [archival register, s. XVII-XVIII] N. 4 blattern von Pastoren Johan Crupaeus de 1598 betrifft den Zehenden besonderes der Bellenbergt und... [mentions place-names, among them Ravenstein].
      Both the primary and secondary scripts are German; the leaves were in the parish of Uckerath, where the secondary script was written, by 1598. This quire was kept in a parchment folder, which is now 2/XII/Ger/5 described below. The primary script may once have formed part of the twelfth-century portion (ff. 5-6v) of the Uckerath missal and Liber censuum described above, MS *170/527; in the little that one can decipher here, the hand and the layout are similar. The measurements, however, not only of the page but of the written space and the individual columns, do not match those of the missal, nor does the number of lines per page (36) correspond with that of the missal (33). Whatever their origin, the leaves have certainly had a separate existence for 400 years. Gift of Edmund M. Riese, ca. 1936, along with the missal (*170/527) and with 2/XII/Ger/5.
  - Missal. Germany (Uckerath)., s. XII1; 2/XII/GER/5.
    - 1) f. 1ra: [Dom. VIII(?) post Pentec.] //[ig]nem mittetur. Igitur... [Matthew 7.20-21 = Roman missal, Dom. VII post Pentec.]; Off. Populum humilem s[alvum] f[acies] [Roman missal, Dom. VIII post, Pentec.]; Secre. Deus qui legalium differentias... [Roman missal, Dom. VII post Pentec.]; Comm. Gustate et videte... [Roman missal, Dom. VIII post Pentec.]; Post comm. Tua nos domine medicinalia... [Deshusses 1152].
    - 2) f. 1ra-rb: Feria IIII, Ad Romanos [Rom. 5.8-11]; f. 1rb-va Secundum Marcum [Marc. 9.37-47].
    - 3) f. 1va: Feria VI, Matheum [Matthew 23.13-23).
    - 4) f. 1vb: Dominica IX. Ecce Deus adiuvat... mala inimicis meis et in// [Roman missal, Introitus Dom. IX post Pentec. ].
    - 5) f. 2ra: [Dom. X post Pentec. ]//se exaltat humiliabitur... [Luc. 18.14: Roman missal, Evang. Dom. X post Pentec. ]; Off. Exaltabo te.. .; Secr. Tibi dornine sacrificia.. .[Deshusses 1160); Comm. Honora dominum de tua subslancia.. .; Post comm. Quesumus domine Deus noster ut quos divinis reparare... [Deshusses 1161).
    - 6) f. 2ra-rb: Feria IIII, Ad Corinthios [1 Cor. 6.15-20]; Evang. Qui non est mecum. Require in ... feria.
    - 7) f. 2rb: Feria VI, Lucam [actually, Marc. 2.13-17].
    - 8) f. 2v: Dominica XII. Deus in adiutorium... [Roman missal, Introitus Dom. XII post Pentec.]; Coll. Omnipotens sempiterne Deus qui abundantia pietatis tue... [Deshusses 1162]; Ad Corinthios [2 Cor. 3.4-9; Roman missal, Epist. Dom. XII post Pentec.]; Off. Benedicam dominum... [Roman missal, Grad. Dom. XII post Pentec. ]; Secundum Marcum... lingue eius et loquer// [Marc. 7.31-35]., The text seems to be a transitional stage between the separate sacramentary and lectionary and the new plenary missal.; Parchment, 2 leaves; f. 1, cropped: 360 × 210 (280 × 180 cropped) mm. 2 columns of 28 lines (outer column cropped); f. 2: 360 × 270 (280 × 200) mm. 2 columns of 28 lines, with a surviving vertical strip of the conjugate (215 × 70 mm., 17 incomplete lines of the inner column). Drypoint ruling barely discernible. Spiky ordinary minuscule in brown ink. Primary initials placed outside the written space, alternately red and blue, at times with flourishes of the alternate color; secondary 1-line initials in red; initials in the text alternately red, green, and blue; rubrics in red minuscule. Neumes of St. Gall type.
      Written at Uckerath by the same hand that wrote folios 5-6v of the Uckerath missal, *170/527 above. These leaves may formerly have belonged to that missal, but the evidence is inconclusive; f. 2, which is uncropped, is smaller than the missal's leaves, the measure of the written space is smaller, and the lines per page are fewer. Whatever their origin, the leaves have certainly had a separate existence since the seventeenth century, when they were made into a folder to enclose the quire that is now 1/XII/Ger/4 above; traces of sewing across both leaves; on f. 1v in gothic cursive, s. XVII, “Diese fier uns beschlossen(?)... blatter der Kirchen Uckerath zustand// (tear) //Zubeobachten.” Gift of Edmund M. Riese, ca. 1936, along with the missal (*170/527) and with 1/XII/Ger/4.
  - Gregorian Sacramentary. Spain., s. XIImed or XII2; 1/XII/IBE/1.
    - r-v: //poscentibus ut his qui te auctore... sacris domine misteriis expiati et veniam consequamur// [temporale, from the post com. of the Fer. V post II Dom. Quadrag. to post com. of Fer. III post III Dom. Quadrag.: Deshusses 220-227 “Implorantes domine misericordiam tuam... ,” 229-238]., Parchment, 1 leaf; 337 × 225 (251 × 138) mm. 26 long lines; double bounding lines; ruling hardly discernible, apparently hardpoint. Rounded ordinary minuscule script written in liturgical style; sporadic use of v and bow of d resembling an 8; only one instance (on the verso) of an open-loop e recalling Visigothic script; frequent use of a reverse c-shaped abbreviation mark for b(us) and q(ue). 2-line initials in red capital or uncial; rubrics in red mixed majuscule.
      Written in Spain. Stained by damp. “4” and “6” in modern pencil on the upper recto. The state of preservation suggests that the leaf was part of a codex until recent times.
  - Augustine, Tractatus In Evangelium Ioannis. Central Italy., s. XII1; 1/XII/ITA/1.
    - r-v: //[ido]nei erant ubi erat Christus... sed quos et redemit fraters //rb://[evan]gelii et bono eius odore excitati... et clamabat dicens: Si quis sitit ve[niat]// va://fluent aquae vivae. Quid est... voluptate et capit de corpo[re]// vb://et forma membrorum accenduntur... vivescit purgata conscientia et hauriens// [Augustine, Tractatus 31.10.15-11.9, 31.11.27-32 heading, 32.2.4-21, 32.3.4-5; ed. Willems, CC 36.299, 300, 300-301, 301-302]., Parchment, top portion of 1 leaf; 240 × 350 (215 cropped × 246) mm. 2 columns, of which 24 lines survive; originally ca. 48-50 lines; single bounding lines; drypoint ruling. Late rounded stately Caroline minuscule, showing the peculiar ri ligature; ascenders often wedge-shaped; d appears in two forms, uncial and upright; b(us) and q(ue) abbreviation marks are in the small 7 shape; dark brown ink.
      Written in central Italy. Rubbed and stained on the recto. Used for binding.
  - Homiliary. Central Italy., s. XII1; 2/XII/ITA/2.
    - r-v: //[carn]es sacrificiorum porcinas. Hic vero... Et post filios occisa est et mater. Hecergo de impietatibus... ipsi gloria in secula seculorum. Amen [Passio ss. Machabeorum: BHL no.5108]; Item sermo beati Maximi nempe in nativate eorum. Unum esse spiritum novi ac veteris testamenti etiam Machabeorum [fratrum?] magnanimitas pro[. .] declarat qui (de etermtatis, catchword)//[Ps. Maximus of Turin; PL 57.693]., Parchment, 1 leaf; 520 × 330 (394 × 258) mm. Horizontal catchword in the bottom margin, below the second column of text. 2 columns of 42 lines; double bounding lines, triple between the columns; drypoint ruling. Firm ordinary minuscule script, showing the peculiar ri ligature and verging to gothic; both a form of ampersand and the tironian note 7 for et are used. Title in red minuscule; 4-line initial outlined in red filled with yellow. Folio number 120 on the top recto (s. XV).
      Written in central Italy. Quite damaged and nearly illegible on the verso. Used for binding a sixteenth-century account book: title by an Italian hand (s. XVI) entered among other notes on the verso, “Quattro protocolli, difficile legendi. Per Innocentio de Bernardini da Campo fattore... car(te) 234 dal 1534 al 1551.” A scrap of a label (s. XVI) is pasted on the verso.
  - Gregory the Great, Dialogues. Italy., s. XIImed; 1/XII/ITA/3.
    - r-v: //eas colligi precepit et [in praelo] mitti. Et quamlibet... alii quoque septem fratres ex nomine// v: //Ceteri autem in eo ordine [ex ca]rne educti sunt... sunt ut precibus optineantur// [Gregory, Dial. 1.7-8, 1.8: ed. U. Moricca, Gregorii Magni Dialogi libri IV (Rome 1924)46.15-47.23, 48.5-26]., Parchment, 1 leaf cropped at the top; 275 × 230 (220 cropped × 140) mm. 23 long lines, originally probably 27 long lines; double bounding lines; drypoint ruling. Calligraphic ordinary minuscule, showing an archaizing flat-topped g and slanting a of early type; brown ink. 2-line initials in red; rubrics in bold red minuscule; instructions to the rubricator quite visible, vertically written in the outer margin.
      Written in Italy, most probably in the north. Used for binding. A note by an Italian hand (s. XVII) on the recto may refer to the contents of the book bound with this leaf: “Clavenna 1608,” Clavenna possibly being the name of a village, now Chiavenna, in upper Lombardy.
  - Martyrology. Central Italy., s. XII1; 2/XII/ITA/4.
    - r-v: //emendi causa pergerent Egiptum. Qui sepius... de eo etiam quod cum omnia possit Deus susci// [Vita Hieronymi: PL 22.221-213; BHL no.3871 and 3872]., Parchment, top portion of 1 leaf; 260 × 350 (230 cropped × 245) mm. 2 columns, of which 28 lines survive from an original ca. 50 lines, with a surviving vertical strip of the conjugate (260 × 57 mm., an unidentified Passio); double bounding lines to each column; drypoint ruling. Written in a late rounded Caroline minuscule; dark brown ink. 5-line initial, uncolored pen and ink with stylized leaf motif. Foliation “CLXXV” on top recto (s. XIV).
      Written in central Italy (Tuscany?). Used for binding a notarial register; title in an Italian hand, s. XVII, “Instrumentorum liber, 1619... 1625, A.8... signor Pietro Mario Cianeschi, not(aio).”
  - Gospel Lectionary. Northern Italy., s. XII-XIII; 1/XII/ITA/5.
    - r: completely rubbed.
    - v: //gelizare pauperibus misit me... que procedebant de ore ipsius [Lectio evang. secundum Luc. 4.18-22]; Feria VI secundum Marcum. In illo tempore. Egressus dominus lesus venit in patriam... paucos infirmos impositis mani// [Lectio evang. secundum Marc. 4.1-5; the readings do not agree with either the Roman or the Ambrosian Capitulare evangeliorum]., Parchment, 1 leaf; 260 × 170 (217 × 140) mm. 24 long lines; single bounding lines; ruled in lead. Written in a bold, somewhat crude, ordinary minuscule in liturgical style, verging toward gothic; dark brown ink. 4-line initial in red with simple blue penwork; Initials in the text slashed with red; rubrics in red minuscule.
      Written probably in northern Italy, or possibly in southern Germany. Parchment wrinkled, stained on the verso; completely rubbed on the recto, save traces of rubric. Used for binding, probably as a pastedown.
  - Missal. Northern Italy., s. XII-XIII; 1/XII/ITA/6.
    - r-v: //dete iusti in domino rectos... va In nativitate sancti Georgii martyris... et omnem qui fert// [end of Missa in Dom. II post Pasc.; beginning of Missa s. Georgii; 23 April]., Parchment, top portion of 1 leaf; 155 × 205 (143 cropped × 160) mm. 2 columns, of which 17 lines survive; double bounding lines; ruling in lead. Rounded early gothic book-hand in liturgical style (littera textualis formata); brown ink. 3-line and 7/8-line initials with heavy vine stem motif outlined in red or brown and filled here and there with yellow and red; 2-line initials in yellow outlined in red; initials in the text slashed with yellow; rubrics in red minuscule.
      Written in northern Italy. Badly rubbed on the verso. Used for binding. Scribbles by sixteenth-century hands.
  - Homiliary. Central Italy., s. XIImed; 1/XII/ITA/7.
    - r-v: //eam filii non vide[ant] matrem... rerum imagine Adam// rb: //quia et de latere... usque ad Noe secunda// va://unde dicitur in psalmo... ageret... et novem... [Hom, in Fer. VI post III Dom. Quadrag.: Augustine, Tract. in Ioh. 15.7.13-8.1, 8.6-9.3, 9.10-10.13, Willems, CC 36.153-154]; vb: Presenti... lectio... tanto incrementus (?)... relaturus... // [almost illegible; opening portion of unidentified sermon]., Parchment, incomplete top portion of 1 leaf; 270 × 245 (257 cropped × 205 cropped; original width ca. 235) mm. 2 columns (the inner cropped) of which 23 lines survive; single bounding lines; drypoint ruling. Written in a bold ordinary minuscule in liturgical style, verging on gothic; brown ink. On vb, 10-line initial in yellow outlined in red with ornamental patterns.
      Written in central Italy. Parchment torn, stained and rubbed on the verso. Used for binding; title by an Italian hand (s. XVI) on the verso, “Berardino... dal 1550 al 1562.”
  - Psalter, with gloss. Italy., ca. 1160-1190; 1/XII/ITA/8.
    - ff. 1-2v: //olive et arva non afferent ... in psalmis canentem [Hab. 3.17-19: Canticum Hahacuc, Stegmüller 21g, with marginal and interlinear gloss, apparently the standard glossatura parva]; Canticum Moysi. Audite caeli que loquor... et dicent tibi: quando di// abbreviation marks for b(us) and q(ue) in the shape of a colon with long tail; r and s often go below the line; the peculiar rounded ri ligature occurs; brown ink. On the verso 2 line initial in red majuscules, followed by the opening words of the text in brown small-majuscules; chapter number in red.
      Written in central Italy, probably in the area of Rome. Stained and rubbed on the verso. Used for binding an account book or notarial register: note by an Italian hand (s, XVII) on the verso, “5”. 1608 sino a 63.”
  - Homiliary. Central Italy., s. XIImed; 2/XII/ITA/11.
    - r-v: //vivi. Id est, tu domine de carne virginis factus es.., perrexit Petrus ad crucem, qui repulso timore mortis moriendi ordinem tam acerba passione quaesivit [unidentified sermon on Matthew 16.13-19]; va Sermo sancti Augustini. Beatus Petrus apostolorurn primus domini nostri Iesu Christi tam amator quam negator sicut indicat euuangelium... nec aliud respondenti: amo, quam: pasce oves meas. Commendatis Petro ovibus// [unidentified sermon, Ps. Augustine]., Parchment, 1 leaf, cropped at the bottom; 445 × 310 (413 cropped × 248) mm. 2 columns of which 51 lines survive; single bounding lines (?); drypoint ruling. Late rounded Caroline minuscule script: r and s go below the line; r is also found in the 2-shape; s in majuscule form at the end of words rises above the other letters: d appears in two forms; abbreviation mark for q(ue) in small 7-shape, for b(us) in 7-shape or colon; brown ink. On va, 8-line initial with vine stems and yellow interlaces on red, blue, green, and purple backgrounds; rubrics in mixed uncial, in red; first lines of text in brown mixed uncial.
      Written in central Italy, in a scriptorium maintaining high standards, perhaps in the Umbro-Roman region. Damaged and covered with a strip of paper pasted on the middle of the recto. Used for binding a notarial register: title by an Italian hand (s. XVI) on the recto, “Instrumenta extensa, 3°, Protocollo dalli 20 luglio 1514 sino li 26 maggio 1570, di ca(rte) 81. Con un quinternetto in quarto foglio de c(arte) 8 con poca tavola, mancante di molte carte che principia li 2 settembre 1570 sino li 21 settembre 1570. Sig. Elisio Giovanni Elisii Not(ai)o.”
      Levine, 50 fig. 4.
  - Homiliary. Italy., s. XII2; 2/XII/ITA/12.
    - r-v: //demos [.. .] operatur [.. .] prophete... resurrectio presignat. Hic Iona... Nam qui se a celesti pretio vident redemptos ad celestia non dubitent preparatos [unidentified sermon]; vb Sermo sancti Augustini (in) Die(m) sanctum pasce. Passionem vel resurrectionem domini et salvatoris... quid egerit. Libere enim egit// [Ps. Augustine, serm. 160: PL vol.40.2059]., Parchment, bottom portion of 1 leaf; 290/340 × 310 (190/240 cropped × 223) mm. 2 columns, of which 22/26 lines survive; single bounding lines; drypoint ruling. Written in ordinary minuscule script in liturgical style, verging on gothic; brown ink. On vb, 13-line initial with zoomorphic and floral patterns, painted in yellow, rose, blue; title in red minuscule.
      Written in Italy (central?). Rubbed on the recto. Used for binding, probably an account book or notarial register: partial title by an Italian hand (s. XVI) on the recto, “1570 usque ad. ...” Other sixteenth-century scribbles on the margins.
  - Bible. Central Italy., s. XIIin; 2/XII/ITA/13.
    - r-v: Et factum est verbum domini... et dixit ad eos// rb://immolaverunt hostias domino... dies et Ninive [.. .] viri Ninivite// va://ut faceret eis et non fecit... et iumenta multa. Explicit Ionas propheta [Ion. 1.1-9, 1.16-3.5, 3.10-4.11]; va Incipit prophatio in Micheas prophetam. Temporib// [cf. Stegmüller 526]; vb Incipit argumentum. Micheas de Mosrachim... percusserit iudicis Israel. Explicit argumentum [Stegmüller 525]; vb Incipit Micheas propheta. Verburn domini quod factum est ad Micheam... quasi acervum lapidum// [Mich. 1.1-6]., Parchment, top portion of 1 leaf; 320 × 300 (270 cropped × 245) mm. 2 columns, of which 37 lines survive; originally ca. 55 lines; single bounding lines; drypoint ruling. Developed rounded Caroline minuscule script; olive brown ink. First line of text and colophons in brown small mixed uncial and capital; 12-line initials in yellow with interlaces, paneled with red and blue geometrical patterns; 2-line initials in red uncial; rubrics in large uneven mixed capitals in red; running title in red minuscule, on the recto only.
      Written in central Italy, in the Umbro-Roman region. The fragment belonged to an Atlantic Bible (see 1/XI/ITA/3). Ink faded and stained by water. Used for binding.
  - Martyrology. Central Italy., s. XIImed; 2/XII/ITA/14.
    - ff. 1-2v: //velante sibi Spiritu Sancto tamen secuturam prenoscens providentia... celebremus diem sollempnitate. Auxiliante domino qui vivit et regnat in trinitate per immortalia secula seculorum. Amen [end of an unidentified legend]; f. 1rb-vb Incipit passio sancte Reparatę virginis, Beatorum Christi martyrum gloriosa certamina... et cum mori in crucis patibulo dignatus sit tertia// [Passio s. Reparatae, BHL no.7184b]; f. 2r-v //post Iesu Christi domini nostri gloriosam ascensionem cum beatus Paulus... eos qui unum et verum Deum sancti baptismatis// [Passio s. Dionysi Areopagitae: AS Oct. 4.792 par. 2-793 par. 10, BHL no.2178]., Parchment, 1 bifolium, margins slightly cropped; 410 × 277 (356 × 214) mm. 2 columns of 45 lines; double bounding lines in the inner and outer margins; drypoint ruling. Crude, rather compressed ordinary minuscule script in liturgical style; brown ink. 7-line initial in yellow outlined in red, enclosing white floral patterns on blue background; rubrics in mixed majuscule in red.
      Written in central Italy, possibly in Florence, given the presence of St. Reparata. “1544” (a date?) is noted twice in the lower margin of f. 1.
  - Martyrology. Central Italy., s. XII2/4; 2/XII/ITA/15.
    - r-v: //dicunt de oriente venisse presbiterum. Dicit ei Alexander... sanctus Alexander clamavit eum dicens... // [Passio ss. Alexandri, Eventii et Theoduli: BHL no.266]., Parchment, 1 leaf, damaged at the bottom; ca. 415 × 305 (ca. 320 × 195) mm. 2 columns of 35 (?) lines; single bounding lines; drypoint ruling; pricking in the outer margin. Late rounded calligraphic Caroline minuscule script: d appears in two forms; abbreviations for b(us) and q(ue) marked by a colon; olive brown ink. Initials in the text slashed with red.
      Written in central Italy. Severely damaged by mildew. Scraps of paper, covered by a late sixteenth-century cursive Italian script, are pasted on the recto. Used for binding a notarial register: title by an Italian hand (s. XVI), “Ser Pietro Pegli (?) 1574” (1574 is repeated three times).
  - Gospel Lectionary. Italy., s. XII2; 1/XII/ITA/16.